{"tossups": [{"question": "This character declares, \"thou to me art all things under heaven,\" in an embedded sonnet alluding to dreams \"some great good presaging.\" This character recalls, \"I started back, it started back, but pleased I soon returned,\" as she observed the \"smooth wat'ry image\" of her own re6lection. This character's \"unadorned golden tresses\" wave \"in wanton ringlets...as the vine curls her tendrils,\" in contrast to the shoulder-length \"hyacinthine locks\" of her husband. This character wonders at the \"language of man pronounced by tongue of brute\" when a creature \"erect amidst his circling spires\" praises her, a7ter which he o5fers to lead her to the tree whose fruit gave him the power of speech. A squadron of angels with a 6laming sword drive this character and her husband from the title location of an English epic. For 10 points, name this character from Paradise Lost, the wife of Adam.", "answer": "Eve", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "After defeating Eurylochus at the Battle of Olpae, a man of this name allowed his Spartan enemies to escape and get into a squabble with the Ambraciots. In another victory, a commander of this name encircled Epitadas' hoplite unit with redeployed trireme rowers carrying rocks. In 425 B.C., a general of this name fortified Pylos into a safe haven for escaped helots, then won the naval Battle of Pylos to maroon 400 Spartiates on an island in Navarino Bay. That general's capture of those Spartan prisoners at the Battle of Sphacteria forced Sparta to agree to the Peace of Nicias. That general, who was executed with Nicias after the Sicilian Expedition, shares this name with a man who shaved half his head to force himself to stay inside and hone his craft. This name is shared by a rival of Aeschines whose \"On the Crown\" speech recounts his history of opposing Macedon. For 10 points, give this name shared by an Athenian general and the Greek orator who delivered ten Philippics.", "answer": "Demosthenes", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In this play, a man's sudden appearance in a doorway \"as though from the air\" interrupts an argument in which another man exclaims \"The promise that a stallion gives a mare I gave that girl!\" after grabbing his rifle. In this play's second act, a man observes \"we are only what we always were, but naked now. Aye, naked! And the wind, God's icy wind, will blow!\" as the curtain falls on a girl sobbing \"I cannot, I cannot,\" over and over. In this play, a man is berated for suggesting other people \"think to go like saints,\" after which he says, \"I speak my own sins; I cannot judge another,\" then angrily cries out, \"I have no tongue for it.\" That man in this play is hanged after insisting, \"I have given you my soul; leave me my name!\" The first act of this play ends with the gleeful cries of a fever-stricken Betty Parris, who rises from bed and joins Abigail in shouting accusations such as \"I saw Goody Hawkins with the Devil!\" For 10 points, name this play about John Proctor set during the Salem Witch Trials and written by Arthur Miller.", "answer": "The Crucible", "subcategory": "American Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This anthropologist developed the \"closed corporate community\" framework to understand why Mesoamerican and Javanese peasant economies exhibited similar behavior. He studied the formation of ideologies under social stress among the Kwakiutl, the Aztecs, and the Nazis in his book Envisioning Power. During the Vietnam War, he collaborated with Marshall Sahlins to lead the 3rst \"teach-in\" at Michigan. In his major work, this author critiqued the static conception of culture, which he rede3ned as a \"series of processes\" that \"construct, reconstruct, and dismantle\" existing cultural symbolism in response to \"identi3able determinants.\" In that book, this anthropologist identi3ed \"kin-ordered,\" \"tributary,\" and \"capitalist\" modes of production, and analyzed cultural transformations among displaced peasants and colonized peoples in response to the over6lows of industrial capitalism. For 10 points, name this Marxist anthropologist who wrote Europe and the People Without History.", "answer": "Eric Wolf", "category": "Social Science", "subcategory": "Social Science"}, {"question": "Labeling biomolecules with ma\u00c2\u00b7le\u00c2\u00b7im\u00c2\u00b7ide requires 3rst applying T\u00c2\u00b7C\u00c2\u00b7E\u00c2\u00b7P to cleave any occurrences of this functional group. Iodo\u00c2\u00b7acet\u00c2\u00b7amide is an alkylating agent used to block the formation of this functional group. Ammonium glycolate cleaves this functional group. A coenzyme that contains a bond of this type in a 3ve-membered ring uses a \"swinging arm\" to carry the acetyl group between the E1 and E3 subunits of the pyruvate de\u00c2\u00b7hydrogenase complex. A six-membered ring containing this functional group and two alcohols occurs in the oxidized form of DTT. A seleno\u00c2\u00b7cysteine-containing peroxidase catalyzes the dimerization of a tri\u00c2\u00b7peptide antioxidant by forming one of these functional groups. Sweetening gasoline involves catalyzing the synthesis of these bonds to reduce gas odor and toxic emissions. Beta\u00c2\u00b7mercapto\u00c2\u00b7ethanol is used to reduce these bonds before a protein is run on a PAGE gel. For 10 points, name this functional group formed when two cysteines are oxidized, named for the presence of two atoms of a certain element.", "answer": "disulfide bonds or bridges [prompt on cysteines or cystines]", "subcategory": "Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "During a conversation about history in this novel, a character describes the human Will standing alone in a public square, where his 6lesh melts o5f when the God of Inevitability proclaims that Chance does not exist. In another episode from this novel, two exchange students si7t through two hundred yards of wet grass for an emerald-set gold ring engraved with the faces of two yaksha. In this novel, the maid Tadeshina (tah-day-SHEE-nah) helps a teenager who keeps a prophetic dream-diary arrange secret trysts with a woman from the declining Ayakura family. At the end of this novel, Satoko joins Gesshu Temple to become a nun, causing her lover to become deathly ill and promise to see his friend again \"beneath the falls.\" Set during the early Taisho era, this novel follows a young member of the upstart Matsugae (mah-tsu-GAH-eh) clan with three moles on his le7t side, which reappear on his subsequent incarnations as Isao and Ying Chan. For 10 points, name this novel about the friends Kiyoaki Matsugae and Shigekuni Honda, the 3rst novel in Yukio Mishima's Sea of Fertility tetralogy.", "answer": "Spring Snow [or Haru no Yuki; prompt on the Sea of Fertility]", "subcategory": "World Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This country's government juiced up the economy with debt-3nanced \"Pharaoh projects\" and the \"correction for in6lation\" scheme. In this country, the October 8 Revolutionary Movement ransomed US Ambassador Charles Burke Elbrick for 37teen prisoners. This country's government responded to the March of the Hundred Thousand student-led protest by cracking down on its \"restricted democracy\" with the Fi7th Institutional Act. A focal point for dissent in this country was the death of journalist Vladimir Herzog in an OBAN facility. Incremental reforms in this country, under the banner of \"opening\" and \"distension,\" gave rise to the oppositional slogan \"Direct elections now!\" The Johnson administration approved Operation Brother Sam, which backed a coup against this country's democratic Goulart (goh-LAHRT) government. From 1964 to 1985, this country was controlled by a military junta, whose working-class opposition coalesced into the Workers' Party. For 10 points, name this country whose authoritarian government tortured future president Dilma Rousseff.", "answer": "Federative Republic of Brazil [or Repu\u0301blica Federativa do Brasil]", "subcategory": "World History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In the Thebaid, Statius explicitly writes that the outcome of one of these events foreshadows that Adrastus will be the only survivor of the Seven Against Thebes. A participant in one of these events mentions a king named Echetus who kills everyone who comes near him and recounts the story of how Eurytion's drunkenness led to the war between the Lapiths and Centaurs in an unsuccessful attempt to dissuade a bystander from becoming involved. The participants in that one of these events make use of a huge ball of lard brought by the goatherd Melanthius. In the Aeneid, an omen likened to a shooting star occurs during one of these events, a7ter which Aeneas gives an engraved bowl to Acestes. At the funeral games of Patroclus, Meriones defeats Teucer in this event. For 10 points, name this type of contest that Odysseus wins immediately before slaughtering the suitors of Penelope.", "answer": "archery contests [prompt on funeral games or marriage contests]", "category": "Mythology", "subcategory": "Mythology"}, {"question": "Cells undergoing this process can be identi3ed by the Thy1 (\"thigh\" \"one\") marker in 6low cytometry and have a lineage denoted Sca-1 positive, c-kit positive, and lin negative. Those cells can also be identi3ed by plating them on a stromal feeder layer and observing the formation of a cobblestone-like region. Purpuras caused by the occurrence of this process outside of its normal location can lead to blueberry mu53n babies. That extra\u00c2\u00b7medulla\u00c2\u00b7ry form of this process occurs in the thymus, liver, and spleen. Colony-stimulating factors direct the di5ferent branches of this process. This process begins with either a common myeloid or common lymphoid progenitor derived from one of its namesake stem cells. The kidney secretes a hormone that stimulates this process known as erythropoietin and it occurs predominantly in the bone marrow. For 10 points, name this process in which blood cells are made.", "answer": "hemato\u00c2\u00b7poiesis (hee-MAT-oh-poy-EE-sihs) [or hemo\u00c2\u00b7poiesis; or hemato\u00c2\u00b7genesis; or speci3c forms, such as erythro\u00c2\u00b7poiesis, lympho\u00c2\u00b7poiesis, and myelo\u00c2\u00b7poiesis; or obvious equivalents, such as making blood cells, until \"blood cells\" is read]", "subcategory": "Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Judge Fuld of the New York Court of Appeals held that a company in this industry could avoid liability by contributing one asset each into ten separate corporations in the seminal veil-piercing case Walkovszky v. Carlton. Fiorello LaGuardia con3scated police billy clubs to prevent clashes during a months-long strike of this industry sparked by an unpopular nickel tax. In London, workers in this industry are required to study for up to four years for a comprehensive test known as \"the Knowledge.\" In Paris in 2016, thousands of striking workers in this industry blocked tra53c to the airports and set tire 3res in the streets. The largest player in this industry in San Francisco declared bankruptcy due to the shrinking value of its \"medallions,\" the licenses required to enter this industry in many American cities. For 10 points, name this industry that has lost signi3cant market share to the ride-sharing apps Ly7t and Uber.", "answer": "regulated taxi industry", "category": "Current Events", "subcategory": "Current Events"}, {"question": "Samuel Eliot Morison's history of this document argued that Article III, which provided tax support for \"Protestant teachers of piety,\" slipped through without a valid two-thirds vote. An early draft of this document was rejected thanks to the arguments of Theophilus Parsons, whose description of the need for \"vigour, secrecy, and dispatch\" was paraphrased in Federalist 70. This document required governors to hold one thousand pounds of property, in accordance with its author's earlier Thoughts on Government. The slaves Elizabeth Freeman and Quock Walker won suits for freedom on the basis of this document's \"Declaration of Rights,\" which began, \"All men are born free and equal.\" This document was the earliest to implement Montesquieu's separation of powers between an executive, an independent judiciary, and a bicameral legislature. It adopted many of its provisions from a political lobby that John Hancock nicknamed the \"Essex Junto.\" For 10 points, name this oldest continuously valid constitution in history, adopted in 1780 a7ter being authored by James Bowdoin, Samuel Adams, and John Adams.", "answer": "the State Constitution of Massachusetts", "subcategory": "American History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "In the Netherlands, an artist with this attribute created an installation called the \"Arnhem Trolleybus Station\" and was known as the \"King of Stations.\" A Victorian artist with this attribute painted cute cats playing at human activities, such as golf. Hans Prinzhorn published a collection of artworks by people with this attribute that was a major in6luence on Jean Dubu5fet, who accordingly studied Adolf Wol6li. Another artist with this attribute depicted his father as an apothecary in the top right of a detailed painting in which a woodsman prepares to split a hazelnut with an axe with Oberon and Titania watching. In a series of paintings of people with this attribute, a man wears a black cap and a medal signifying military command, and the white-bonneted \"Hyena of Salpetriere\" (sahl-pet-ree-AIR) has red-rimmed eyes representing envy. Etienne-Jean Georget (zhor-ZHAY) commissioned Theodore Gericault to create a series of portraits of people with this attribute. For 10 points, identify this class of people that includes many \"outsider artists\" and several people housed with Vincent van Gogh in Saint-Remy.", "answer": "the insane [or equivalents, such as schizophrenics; or mad people; or asylum inmates; prompt on outsider artists]", "subcategory": "Visual Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Observables for these objects that have one-over-Q power dependence include a universal two-loop correction term called the Milan factor. Measurements of these objects are complicated by \"splash-in\" e5fects like underlying event and pile-up contamination. The anti-k-sub-t algorithm is the standard method for reconstructing these objects because it does not create \"dark towers\" and is una5fected by di5fuse radiation, in addition to being infrared- and collinear-safe. These objects appear cone-shaped when graphing transverse momentum versus pseudorapidity and azimuthal angle for an array of calorimeters on a lego plot. The Ellis-Karliner angle characterizes collisions that produce three of these objects, which provide experimental evidence for the existence of gluons. For 10 points, name these collimated energy signatures that are detected in particle accelerators due to the hadronization of free quarks.", "answer": "particle jets [or particle showers; or particle sprays; prompt on energy signatures; do not accept \"resonances\" or \"particles\" or \"quarks\" or \"gluons\" or \"hadrons\" or any other answer that refers to individual particles]", "subcategory": "Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "One 3lm includes a close-up of the trembling hand of a member of this organization as he tries to get a 6ly crawling on a broken grate to step onto his 3nger. Another 3lm, about two brothers in this organization, ends with a long shot of one of the brothers wheeling his motorcycle away from a woman moaning over a letter he had just given her along with a pendant. In that 3lm, members of this organization watch from hiding as men violently shave that woman's head and force her to watch her house burn. In another 3lm, a 17-minute static long take of two men smoking and talking at a table leads into a recollection about drowning a dying foal on a cross-country team trip, which a member of this organization uses to justify his actions to a priest. In that 3lm, depictions of the brutality during this organization's \"blanket\" and \"no-wash\" protests are followed by a lengthy sequence of a prisoner's body deteriorating under the title condition. For 10 points, name this organization depicted in Ken Loach's The Wind That Shakes the Barley and Steve McQueen's Hunger, in which Michael Fassbender plays Bobby Sands.", "answer": "the IRA [or the Irish Republican Army]", "subcategory": "Other Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Surveyors of these institutions abhorred the shocking prevalence of \"daughter-in-law rights,\" in which fathers chose wives for their underage sons so they could rape them. Liberals responded to August von Haxthausen's (HOCKST-\"how\"-zen's) valorization of these institutions by tracing their origin back to 18th-century tax policies. Young people labeled \"propagandists\" to these institutions were rounded up and imprisoned for the \"Trial of the 193.\" A reform to these institutions was pitched as a \"wager on the strong and sober.\" During the \"Mad Summer of '74,\" students recalled from Switzerland donned shoddy clothes to join these institutions as part of the \"going to the people\" movement. Early 20th-century reforms sought to eliminate their periodic \"repartitions\" by replacing these institutions with otrub and khutors. These institutions were made into a national symbol by the Slavophile movement and idealized as embryonic socialism by the narodniki. For 10 points, name these peasant communes in Tsarist Russia.", "answer": "obshchina [or mir; or peasant communes in Russia before \"Russia\" is read; prompt on peasant communes; do not prompt on \"collective farms\"]", "subcategory": "European History", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This concept was the subject of a 2003 book by Gregory Currie and Ian Ravenscro7t focusing on what they de3ne as its \"recreative\" form. Kant discussed the \"transcendental\" form of this concept in the 3rst edition of his Critique of Pure Reason, but omitted it from the subsequent editions. Christopher Hill's writings on this concept have drawn on Thomas Nagel's lengthy footnote in \"What Is It Like to Be a Bat?\" distinguishing between the \"perceptual\" and \"sympathetic\" forms of this concept. Kant identi3ed this concept with the synthesis of reproduction, which he grouped along with apprehension and recognition as one of the three mental faculties. This faculty's \"primary\" form was identi3ed as \"the living power and prime agent of all human perception\" by Samuel Taylor Coleridge, who contrasted this faculty with another that merely rearranges preexisting materials in his distinction between this faculty and \"fancy.\" For 10 points, name this mental faculty used in creating works of art.", "answer": "imagination [or imagining]", "category": "Philosophy", "subcategory": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "In a midrash, the Emperor Hadrian mocks a 100-year-old man for engaging in this action, but rewards him with gold a year later. Rabbi Johanan ben Zakkai told his followers that if they were doing this action when the Messiah came, to 3nish it before greeting him. Leviticus 19:23 includes the orlah, a three-year period a7ter completing this action during which it is forbidden to bene3t from it, followed by a year in which only Israel may bene3t. A passage in the Babylonian originated the custom of doing this upon the birth of a child to prepare for its eventual marriage. The Jewish National Fund, which annually helps 80,000 tourists complete this action in Israel, claims to have done it 250 million times as part of its central mission. In the twentieth century, it became the central ritual of the agricultural new year celebrated on Tu BiShvat. For 10 points, name this action which, when done upon the birth of a child, later provides building material for a chuppah.", "answer": "planting trees [or planting a  g tree]", "category": "Religion", "subcategory": "Religion"}, {"question": "In a short story, a young man tasked with picking out one of these beings among a group of maidens playing \"hawk and chickens\" is rewarded with a mysterious letter for his father the mayor. In that story, the iron claws of one of these beings leave marks on the throat of a maiden, who chops o5f its hand and drowns herself in the pond beside her father's house. In another story, one of these beings stomps on the earth, turning it translucent with 3re and enabling a youth to see the treasure buried under his feet. In that story, a man su5fering from amnesia regains his memory upon seeing one of these beings and throws his ax at her, recalling how she drank the blood of the boy Ivas in Bear's Ravine. Basavriuk (bah-SAHV-ree-uck) introduces Petro to one of these beings in Nikolai Gogol's story \"St. John's Eve.\" Another character trashes the literary critic Latunsky's apartment a7ter becoming one of these beings by smearing Azazello's cream on her naked body. For 10 points, name these supernatural beings, examples of whom include Margarita a7ter she makes a deal with Woland and gains the ability to 6ly.", "answer": "witches [prompt on cats]", "subcategory": "European Literature", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "Dividing the area over which this phenomenon occurs into multiple discrete sections increases the isoplanatic patch radius. The Tatarski model of this phenomenon assumes a Gaussian random distribution with a second-order structure function. SCIDAR and the Hufnagel-Valley model are methods for constructing the C-sub-N squared pro3le of this phenomenon in order to compute the Greenwood time constant and Fried coherence length. A technique for mitigating the e5fects of this phenomenon uses a reference laser tuned to the 589.2 nanometer emission line of sodium in order to create a guide star. Other corrective devices for this phenomenon include Shack-Hartmann wavefront sensors and MEMS-based deformable mirrors. For 10 points, name this phenomenon that motivates the development of adaptive optics because it limits the resolution of images taken at astronomical observatories.", "answer": "atmospheric turbulence [or optical turbulence; or atmospheric distortion; or astronomical seeing; or speckle patterns; or twinkling; or scintillation; prompt on turbulence; prompt on image distortion or similar answers describing problems with telescopes; do not accept \"atmospheric extinction\"]", "subcategory": "Other Science", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "Note to players: composer and type of piece required. Many parts in these musical compositions were written for their composer's students Giulia Frasi and Caterina Galli. The composition of these works resulted in the incidental invention of the organ concerto, since their composer wrote and played his organ concertos as interludes during them. Near the end of their composer's life, an early one of these compositions in Italian was reworked by Thomas Morell. In the last of these compositions, written while their composer was going blind, the second part concludes with the chorus \"How dark, O Lord, are thy decrees.\" The success of these works inspired their composer to abandon Italian opera, a genre in which he had composed such successes as Giulio Cesare (JOO-lee-oh CHEH-zah-ray), Rinaldo, and Agrippina. Charles Jennens wrote the libretti for several of these compositions, including one featuring the iconic \"Hallelujah\" Chorus. For 10 points, name these compositions by a German-British composer, exemplified by Messiah.", "answer": "oratorios by George Frideric Handel [prompt on oratorios]", "subcategory": "Auditory Fine Arts", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A short poem by this poet begins and ends all 3ve stanzas with the words \"now\" and \"me,\" respectively, as in, \"Now lies the earth all Danae to the stars, and all thy heart lies open unto me.\" Another of his poems spoken by a shepherd instructs a maid to \"cease...to set a star upon the sparkling spire\" and \"let the wild lean-headed eagles yelp alone,\" inviting her to the valley where she will hear \"the moan of doves in immemorial elms, and murmuring of innumerable bees.\" Another poem by this man invokes \"the 3rst beam glittering on a sail that brings our friends up from the underworld\" and \"the earliest pipe of half-awakened birds to dying ears\" in a series of similes leading into nostalgic refrains about \"the days that are no more.\" His narrative poem The Princess includes the interpolated lyrics \"Now sleeps the crimson petal,\" \"Come down, O maid,\" and \"Tears, idle tears.\" For 10 points, name this Victorian poet who also wrote \"The Lady of Shalott.\"", "answer": "Alfred, Lord Tennyson", "subcategory": "British Literature", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}